The Eiffel Tower was built for the Centennial Exposition of 1889, a fair to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the French Revolution. It was designed and constructed by French engineer Alexandre Gustave Eiffel, who was subsequently nicknamed the Magician of Iron after the tower was completed. It was finished in early 1889, in a shroud of amazement and criticism. The tower was widely disliked by many of the artists, writers and citizens of the day. Well known artists wrote that the tower was "useless and monstrous" much like the tower of Babel. The design would eventually vindicate itself of this criticism, as the structure was sound, and there was an air of aesthetic beauty to it.

The tower was raised in just a few months with a small labor force and a relatively low cost. It was opened for the Exposition on June 10, 1889, and Eiffel spent the day ushering royalty to the top, showing off his magnificent piece of work. In the next few weeks, people such as the Shah of Persia, the Prince of Wales, the King of Siam, the Bey of Djibouti, the President of France, Buffalo Bill, and Thomas Edison were guests of the Eiffel Tower. More than 1.9 million people would visit the monument during the exposition.

The actual structure of the tower itself was highly advanced for the time period. It consisted of four semi-circular arches at the base with iron trusses along the sides. It was constructed entirely of iron and steel. The original tower was 300 meters high, making it the tallest free standing, man-made structure in the world at the time, finally being surpassed with the completion of the Chrysler Building in New York City in 1930. It was twice as tall as the dome of St. Peter's Cathedral in Rome or the great pyramids of Giza. The first level, the largest of the three, has been built into a museum called the Cinemax, where videos are shown about the history of the tower and its construction. The central structure consists of two levels, each of which has a restaurant. The third level is the Salle Gustave Eiffel, or Eiffel Hall, which has space for business conferences, expositions, cultural events, and other social gatherings.

After the 1889 exposition, Eiffel knew that he would have to find a practical use for his monument or it would be destroyed by the immense amount of criticism coming from the public. He teamed up with the French Central Weather Bureau in 1890, attaching thermometers, barometers, and anemometers to the top of the tower to record various weather readings and conditions. In 1909, he began a study of aerodynamics, building the first successful wind tunnel on top of the tower. Many of the artists were very jealous of the work that Eiffel had constructed, and they created a great deal of confusion and false rumors in an attempt to try and have his image ruined in the public's eye. They were somewhat successful for a time, until people began to see that this enormous structure was in fact a practical, useful piece of work, as well as being aesthetically beautiful. Today the Eiffel Tower is one of the most famous and most recognized monuments in the history of the world.
