D-Type Text Layout Extension (available standalone or as part of D-Type PowerDoc Engine) uses the ICU Layout Engine to support world's complex scripts. The LayoutEngine does all the work necessary to display Unicode text written in languages with complex writing systems such as Hindi (हिन्दी), Thai (ไทย) and Arabic (العربية).

Here's a sample of some text written in Sanskrit:
श्रीमद् भगवद्गीता अध्याय अर्जुन विषाद योग धृतराष्ट्र उवाच। धर्मक्षेत्रे कुरुक्षेत्रे समवेता युयुत्सवः मामकाः पाण्डवाश्चैव किमकुर्वत संजय

Here's a sample of some text written in Arabic: أساسًا، تتعامل الحواسيب فقط مع الأرقام، وتقوم بتخزين الأحرف والمحارف الأخرى بعد أن تُعطي رقما معينا لكل واحد منها. وقبل اختراع "يونِكود"، كان هناك مئات الأنظمة للتشفير وتخصيص هذه الأرقام للمحارف، ولم يوجد نظام تشفير واحد يحتوي على جميع المحارف الضرورية and here's a sample of some text written in Thai: บทที่๑พายุไซโคลนโดโรธีอาศัยอยู่ท่ามกลางทุ่งใหญ่ในแคนซัสกับลุงเฮนรีชาวไร่และป้าเอ็มภรรยาชาวไร่บ้านของพวกเขาหลังเล็กเพราะไม้สร้างบ้านต้องขนมาด้วยเกวียนเป็นระยะทางหลายไมล์
